You know, usually when we talk about a medical diagnosis, there is this deep, almost unconscious expectation of precision.
Oh, absolutely. We want it to be clean.
Right. We want it to feel like engineering.
So imagine you fall off a ladder, you break your arm, and you go to the hospital.
You're sitting in that cold room with the plastic chairs, smelling the antiseptic.
I can picture it. It's not a great place to be.
No, it's awful.
Yeah.
But eventually, the doctor puts your x-ray up on the light board, and there is that jagged, glowing white line across the bone.
The doctor just points a pen at it and says, you know, there it is. That is the problem.
And honestly, it is incredibly comforting in a strange way.
It really is, because it's binary.
Exactly. Broken or not broken, it is undeniably visible.
The ambiguity of your pain is suddenly cleanly categorized into a physical object you can literally point to.
A completely clean distinction. And I think we carry that desire for a clean binary snapshot into almost every other aspect of our lives.
Oh, without a doubt.
But then you step into the world of human identity. You step into the mechanics of consciousness or, you know, how we actually move through time.
And suddenly that x-ray machine is completely useless.
Totally useless. Yet we still crave those snapshots, don't we?
I mean, we want a driver's license or a credit score or even a personality test to do the exact same thing that the medical scan does.
We want to point to a piece of paper and say, ah, there I am. That static picture is me.
Right. Which, as we're going to see today, is entirely a cognitive illusion.
Because your true identity, I mean, structurally speaking, isn't that frozen snapshot at all?
No, it's not.
If we go back to your broken arm, the reality of that arm isn't the single frame of the x-ray.
The reality is the entire messy, irreversible history of how that specific bone grew over decades.
Like the childhood diet, the genetics, all of it.
Exactly. The exact velocity and angle at which it fractured, the biological cascade of how it healed over months,
and even every single step you chose to take or are favored slightly differently for the rest of your life because of that injury.
It's a living, breathing, irreversible log of events.
It is.
And the overarching thesis we are exploring in this deep dive today is that the moment we try to freeze that log into a static snapshot,
the moment we try to reduce a human being to an x-ray or a data point,
we actually destroy the very structural integrity that makes you you.
And that structural destruction isn't just a philosophical metaphor.
According to the incredibly dense research we are unpacking today, it is a literal mathematical crisis.
Like a crisis that is tearing apart our digital and economic systems right now.
Yes, exactly.
Which brings us to the mission for this deep dive.
Today, we are immersing ourselves in a truly radical, mathematically rigorous paper published in March 2026.
A very recent, very heavy piece of work.
Very heavy.
The author goes by the handle Flyxion, or Flyxion, depending on how you pronounce it.
And the paper is titled Process, Projection, and Power Toward a Unified Ontology of Choice, Causality, and Value.
Quite a mouthful.
It is.
And alongside that, we will be deeply exploring the core theorems of an interconnected framework known as the compiled self.
I just have to say, it is a staggering amount of material to synthesize.
The ambition of this author is off the charts.
Right.
They are attempting to build a single, cohesive, formal, mathematical architecture that connects the deepest physical mysteries of time straight up through the cognitive experience of human consciousness and all the way out into the macroeconomics of global coordination.
It's basically a theory of everything, but applied to human identity.
Exactly.
So our goal today is to decode this architecture for you, the listener.
We're going to look under the hood of reality itself.
We'll explore why classical physics fails to explain what it feels like to be alive.
A huge topic on its own.
For sure.
We'll also cover how human identity is mathematically constructed from moment to moment, and why modern algorithms, the ones currently running our society, are mathematically guaranteed to degrade that identity by flattening it into what the paper calls one-dimensional slop.
We are also going to look at the geometry of how you make choices.
And perhaps most importantly, we will examine the highly technical blueprint the author proposes at the end of the paper.
The cure, basically.
Right.
A new computational grammar designed to save complex digital and economic systems from total collapse.
It is a massive intellectual journey.
But before we really get into the mechanics of the math and the philosophy, I want to take a moment to be completely transparent with you.
Yeah, we need a quick disclaimer here.
Right.
Because the sources we are working from today dive fearlessly into some incredibly heavy systemic critiques.
The text aggressively analyzes capitalism, the consolidation of corporate power, economic extraction, and institutional decay.
It uses these economic models to literally prove its mathematical points.
The systemic analysis is woven directly into the topology of the math.
The author does not separate the physics of time from the realities of modern labor.
Exactly.
Because of that, I need to explicitly state that our mission today is to impartially report on the math and the frameworks provided in these texts.
We are not endorsing any political, economic, or ideological viewpoints.
We are not taking sides on the paper's systemic critiques.
Right.
We are simply acting as your guides, exploring the profound and honestly mind-bending concepts contained in this text to see what we can learn from the architecture it proposes.
And if we are going to understand this new architecture, this math of the compiled self, we have to start by completely demolishing our default assumptions about how the universe works.
We have to start at the very bottom layer of reality.
We do.
Let's do it.
So, in classical science, basically, since the Enlightenment and Isaac Newton, we have treated reality as being fundamentally made up of static objects.
Right.
We look around and we think the universe is a giant container.
And inside that container are things.
Particles, planets, chairs, people, dollars.
And then as a secondary phenomenon, those things occasionally move or change state.
This is what Flyxion refers to as an ontology of being.
Okay.
Unpack that term for us.
Well, ontology is just the philosophical study of what actually exists.
So, an ontology of being is the core assumption that static stuff matter, objects, isolated entities, is the primary ingredient of reality.
I always think of it like a game of pool.
In classical science, we treat the universe like a set of billiard balls sitting motionless on a green felt table, just waiting for the cue ball to strike them.
That's a great visual.
The being, the static ball, is the default state of the universe.
The doing the movement across the table is just an accidental property that happens to the being when force is applied.
That is the perfect way to visualize the classical mindset.
But Flyxion's paper completely inverts that paradigm.
It argues that classical science is looking at reality entirely backward.
Backward how?
The paper proposes what it calls an ontology of becoming.
In this framework, transitions, choices, processes, the irreversible changes from one state to another, those are not accidents happening to static objects.
The transitions are the actual fundamental building blocks of reality.
Okay, wait.
So, the doing is the default?
The doing is the only fundamental reality.
Everything we think of as a static object is actually just a secondary projection.
Like a shadow.
Exactly.
It's a temporary shadow cast by an underlying continuous process.
To use your analogy, there are no billiard balls.
Wait, really?
None?
None.
There is only the continuous process of momentum and collision.
And when that process loops tightly enough in a localized area, it creates the temporary localized illusion of a solid sphere.
Oh, wow.
You, as a human being, are not a static object that occasionally makes a choice.
You are the continuous process of making choices which generates the temporary interface of a person.
That is a total ontological flip.
It takes a second for the brain to even process that because our language is so noun heavy.
Oh, definitely.
We're wired for nouns.
We want to be nouns, but the paper says we are verbs.
And to see why this radical flip is mathematically necessary, we have to look at one of the biggest failures in modern science.
We have to talk about David Chalmers and the hard problem of consciousness.
Because this is exactly where the billiard ball model of the universe completely breaks down.
It really is.
It's the ultimate roadblock for the ontology of being.
For anyone who hasn't encountered this concept, the philosopher David Chalmers formulated the hard problem of consciousness in the 1990s.
And it asks a deceptively simple question.
How does physical matter create subjective experience?
Right.
Because if the universe is just static things bumping into each other, where does the feeling come from?
We can map the neural pathways of the human brain perfectly.
We can look at the x-ray.
We can see the electrical signals jumping across the synapses.
We can map the exact chemistry of serotonin and dopamine.
Exactly.
But none of that physical, mechanical interaction tells us why it feels like something to see the color red or to taste a strawberry or to feel grief.
The physics gives us the blind mechanics, but it completely fails to account for the first-person perspective.
The rich, qualitative, internal experience of being alive.
Right.
Physics can explain how the eye processes a wavelength of light, which is what Chalmers calls the easy problem.
Which isn't actually easy, but comparatively.
Right.
But it cannot explain the experience of redness.
That is the hard problem.
And the text brings in the work of a systems theorist named Forrest Landry here, which I found fascinating.
Landry argues that the reason traditional physics can't solve the hard problem is because of the foundational perspective from which physics is built.
Yes.
Landry points out that when we build physical models of the universe, whether it's Newtonian mechanics or Einstein's relativity,
we construct them exclusively from a third-person perspective.
We step outside of it.
We step outside the universe to look at it as a whole.
And when we do that, we create what physicists call the block universe.
The block universe.
Yeah.
This is the idea that time isn't actually flowing, but that time is just another geometric dimension, exactly like length, width, or height.
Precisely.
In the mathematics of general relativity, every single moment in time, the Big Bang, the moment you were born, the present second, and the eventual heat death of the universe, it all exists simultaneously as a static four-dimensional block.
It's all just there.
In those physical equations, time is perfectly symmetric.
You can run the math forward or you can run the math backward, and the equations work exactly the same.
There is no mathematical distinction between the past and the future.
I always try to visualize the block universe like a digital movie file sitting on my computer's hard drive.
Okay.
I like that.
The entire movie, from the opening credits to the end scene, exists simultaneously on the disk.
The physics equations give us the progress bar at the bottom of the screen, and that progress bar is perfectly symmetric.
As an observer outside the movie, I can drag my mounts and click to minute two, or I can click to minute 90.
It's all equally accessible data.
Right.
That is the third-person block universe view of reality.
It is a brilliant mathematical model for calculating planetary orbits, but it has a fatal flaw when it comes to human reality.
Because that is absolutely not how you and I actually experience reality.
It isn't.
Not even close.
No, we don't experience our lives as a symmetric progress bar where we can jump back to yesterday.
We experience time as a relentless, moving laser.
We are the playhead on the progress bar, reading exactly one frame of reality at a time.
That's a great way to put it.
The playhead.
The first-person perspective is the playhead.
As it moves, it leaves a trail of watched frames behind it, the fixed, irreversible past.
And it looks forward into an unplayed buffer, the open, undetermined future.
The block universe progress bar might be symmetric, but the playhead's journey is aggressively, violently asymmetric.
It only goes in one direction.
And classical science, because it only believes in the third-person block universe, has no explanation for the playhead.
They just ignore it.
In fact, many strict materialist physicists will argue that the feeling of, you know, the sensation of time passing is literally just a psychological illusion.
They argue that the static progress bar is the objective reality, and your subjective feeling of the playhead moving is just a trick your brain is playing on you.
Which feels incredibly insulting to my daily experience, frankly.
Oh, absolutely.
But here is where Flickshinian's paper introduces its radical solution to the hard problem.
The paper says, no, the physicists have it backwards.
The static block universe, the progress bar, is the mathematical abstraction.
The moving playhead is the fundamental reality of the universe.
This is the core of the ontology of becoming.
The paper argues that consciousness isn't some magical, ethereal substance floating in your head.
It isn't some emergent smoke that gets magically generated when brain cells get complex enough.
Consciousness is the fundamental internal experience of temporal asymmetry.
Let's slow down and really unpack that.
Consciousness is the internal experience of temporal asymmetry.
So going back to the playhead.
Consciousness is just the friction of that playhead moving forward.
In a sense, yes.
Think about what is actually happening at the present moment.
You are standing at the edge of the present.
In front of you is a space of multiple, undetermined, possible futures.
You have to make a choice.
The moment you make a choice, you collapse all those myriad possibilities into a single, fixed, irreversible historical fact.
You take the fluid future and you forge it into the solid past.
And that transition from possibility to fixed history is mathematically asymmetric.
You can't undo it.
Exactly.
And what Flyxion argues is that this physical collapse, this transition from many futures to one past, has an internal subjective aspect to it.
That internal aspect is consciousness.
Wow.
Subjective experience is simply what it feels like from the inside to be the process that resolves possibilities into history.
We are not static biological objects that somehow possess consciousness as a property.
We are the active, irreversible process of time flowing.
And the feeling of being alive is the sensation of that flow.
Okay.
My mind is already stretched to its limits.
We have shifted from a universe made of static billiard balls to a universe made of pure process, transition, and flow.
Yes.
The problem of consciousness is solved by realizing we're the flow of time.
But this immediately raises a huge, terrifying question for me.
Which is?
If reality is just this endless, continuous sequence of transitions, if there is no solid, static stuff at the bottom of it all, how do we not just dissolve into pure chaos?
If I am not a physical object, but just a verb, how does a stable me exist at all?
How do I wake up feeling like the same person I was yesterday?
That is the exact tension that drives the entire second major section of the source material.
If we throw out the comforting idea of a static soul locked in a jar, or the idea that your identity is just your physical body, especially since your biological cells are constantly dying and replacing themselves, what is human identity?
Right.
What is holding it together?
Exactly.
The paper introduces a formal, mathematically rigorous architecture to answer this.
It is called the compiled self.
The compiled self.
I love the terminology here.
It implies that identity isn't a pre-existing thing you were handed at birth.
It is an ongoing, dynamically maintained abstraction.
It is something you have to continuously compute.
It is an achievement.
Yes, and to prove why we need this incredibly specific mathematical architecture to maintain an identity, the paper actually starts by showing us what happens when an identity fails to compile.
It shows us a massive structural failure in artificial intelligence.
Yes, the Markov name generator experiment.
The author uses this experiment as a beautiful, isolating proof of concept.
Let's break down exactly what happened.
Please do.
The author built a relatively simple AI system based on a Markov chain.
A Markov chain is essentially a probability engine.
It looks at a current state and predicts the most likely next state based on historical training data.
So in this case, the author trained it on English phonetic rules and historical names.
Correct.
The goal was to generate completely novel, unique names that had never existed before.
The system would look at a letter, say T, and use probability to guess that H or R should come next and then guess the next vowel and so on.
Okay, makes sense.
And on a purely lexical level, the experiment was a massive success.
Oh, yeah.
The names it spit out were fantastic.
They sounded lexically plausible.
They sounded like they could belong to real historical figures or characters in a high fantasy novel.
Names like Fowler or Caelan or Vespera.
They had a beautiful phonetic surface.
But then the author took the experiment to the crucial second stage.
They took these brand new phonetically unique names and fed them into a massive state-of-the-art large language model, a neural network with billions of parameters.
Like the AIs everyone is using today.
Exactly.
And the author prompted the language model.
Here is a name.
Invent a backstory, a mythology, and a distinct personality for this individual.
And the result was an absolute structural collapse.
Complete semantic failure.
No matter how phonetically unique the names were, no matter how different Fowler sounded from Caelan, the language model immediately collapsed their backstories into the exact same handful of generic, repetitive tropes.
Every single time.
Every single name became an ancient, wise, sage living in the woods or a cyclical deity of nature and balance.
The AI created lexical novelty on the surface.
But when asked to generate an identity, it fell into a generic sinkhole.
And the paper meticulously argues that this was not just a temporary glitch or a lack of training data.
It was a mathematical inevitability.
Why did it happen?
Because the generated names lacked what Flyxion calls history coupling.
History coupling.
Let's dig into that.
When the Markov chain generated the word Thaler, each letter was chosen probabilistically in isolation.
The A was chosen because it fit well after the Aish.
But there was no deeper, continuous logic tying the entire name to a lived history.
It was just math.
Just surface math.
The name had no physical or temporal constraints.
It was a surface without a substrate.
It's like generating a shadow without a physical object to cast the shadow.
Exactly.
So when the massive language model looks at that shadow and tries to interpret the person
behind it, it finds nothing to grab onto.
There is no historical friction.
There are no underlying constraints.
And without that...
Without constraints to guide it, the massive probabilistic weight of the language model
just defaults to the densest center of its training data.
It defaults to the most generic, highly repeated archetypes of human myth.
It hallucinates a generic average because the input has no sovereign uniqueness.
So, if unconstrained generation isn't enough to create a distinct identity, if just making
up a random string of letters or actions doesn't make us self-quitting, what is the actual mathematical
requirement for an identity to exist and survive?
This is where we get to the core of the paper.
Flyxion outlines the architecture of identity through four rigorous mathematical theorems.
If you want to exist as a stable, compiled self, you must continuously satisfy these four
conditions.
Okay, let's go through them.
The first one is the abstraction theorem.
Let's unpack the abstraction theorem.
The text states that a stable interface, a stable you that can be recognized and interacted
with over time, only exists if a constraint functional enforces global coherence across your
history.
A constraint functional.
In layman's terms, your identity is mathematically defined by the rules you refuse to break.
Oh, that's interesting.
The accumulated history of what you have done in the past acts as a rigid constraint on what
you are mathematically allowed to do next if you wish to remain you.
I have to admit, when I first read this, I wanted to push back aggressively.
Oh, most people do.
Because culturally, we are taught that true freedom means having infinite options.
We think of our identity as this limitless potential, and constraints are just societal cages
trapping the real me.
If my identity is just an interface, hiding a bunch of contradictory chaotic impulses underneath,
aren't constraints the enemy of my true self?
It's a very intuitive, very human assumption.
But the mathematics of complex systems proves the exact opposite.
Let's look at it structurally.
Imagine you are trying to build a massive skyscraper.
The constraint functional is the physics beneath the architecture, the load-bearing steel beams,
the poured concrete foundation, the strict laws of tension, compression, and gravity.
Right, the stuff holding it out.
If you suddenly decide that constraints are a cage, and you want your building to be infinitely
free, what do you do?
You remove the steel beams, you just start stacking glass panels and drywall on top of each
other in any arbitrary shape you want.
Does the building become infinitely free?
No, it instantly shatters under its own weight.
It ceases to be a building at all, becomes a pile of rubble.
Exactly.
So the constraints are not the cage trapping the building.
The constraints are the bones that allow the building to exist in the first place.
The constraints are the bones.
I love that.
Without them, any new action I take could arbitrarily contradict my past actions, and the coherent
abstraction known as my personality would fracture into noise.
Yes.
I would be a completely different person from millisecond to millisecond.
My family wouldn't recognize me.
I wouldn't recognize myself.
The constraints are what allow an abstraction to cohere over the span of a lifetime.
That is the abstraction theorem.
You must have structural bones.
Which leads us directly to the second pillar, the substrate theorem.
This theorem deals with the physical or digital medium that actually carries your identity.
Because the math has to run on something.
Right.
And the substrate theorem states that whatever medium is hosting your compiled self, it must
have the physical capacity to preserve your spectral signatures.
Spectral signatures.
We are moving from architecture into some heavy signal processing terminology here.
We are, but it's vital for understanding how uniqueness survives.
The paper uses Fourier transforms to explain this concept.
Okay, let's pause.
Walk me through a Fourier transform.
I know it's a way to analyze waves, but how does it apply to human choices?
Let's break it down.
In mathematics, a Fourier transform is a tool that takes a very complex, messy signal, like
the sound of a symphony orchestra, and breaks it apart into its fundamental continuous sine
waves.
Okay.
It reveals the exact frequencies and amplitudes that combine to make that complex sound.
So it finds the hidden rhythm inside the noise.
Exactly.
Now, apply that to the continuous process of your life.
Imagine tracking every choice you make.
The time you wake up, how you react to a stressful email, the cadence of your speech, the specific
way you arrange your kitchen, if you map the continuous process of your choices over years,
it creates a highly complex, multidimensional wave.
Wave of behavior.
And if you run a Fourier transform on that behavioral wave, you get your spectral signature.
It is the deep, fundamental, mathematical frequency of how you navigate possibility space.
That's fascinating.
It is the generative rhythm that makes your choices distinctly yours, separating your specific
process from the generic background noise of human behavior.
That is beautiful.
It's not just a database list of things I've done.
It's the underlying acoustic resonance of my entire existence.
Yes.
And the substrate theorem dictates that your medium, whether it is the biological neural
networks in your human brain, or potentially some future digital substrate, must be high
fidelity enough to physically preserve those delicate frequencies.
And if it isn't?
If the medium is too compressed or too lossy, your unique frequency gets drowned out by the noise,
and your identity cannot be maintained.
Okay, so we have the constrained bones, and we have a high-fidelity medium preserving our
unique behavioral frequency.
What is the third requirement?
The third is the policy theorem.
This outlines the literal mathematics of surviving your own choices over the long term.
It states that a viable compiled identity must continuously balance two opposing forces,
restrictive actions and expansive actions.
Let's ground this in reality.
What happens if I fail to balance them?
Let's say I only take restrictive actions.
I decide the world is too chaotic.
I stay inside my house.
I lock the doors.
I eat the exact same meal every day.
I refuse to read any new books, learn any new skills, or speak to anyone I don't already
know.
What happens to my compiled self?
Mathematically, your volume of possibility space collapses toward zero.
Because you are a process of becoming, if you stop incorporating new information, the
process stagnates.
So I just kind of fade out.
Structurally, yes.
The structural complexity of your identity degrades.
You cease to be a dynamic living system, and you trend toward a dead, static object.
But what if I swing wildly to the other extreme?
What if I only take expansive actions?
I try to be a medical doctor and a concert pianist and a deep sea welder.
I move to a new continent every three days.
I make deep emotional commitments to 10 different people, and then abandon them all to start a
new religion.
That sounds exhausting.
Right.
I constantly contradict my previous history in the name of total exploration.
Then the system explodes.
Mathematically, you accumulate so much constraint tension that the surface tension of your identity
pops.
Remember the bones from the abstraction theorem.
Yeah.
The rules I refuse to break.
By taking on completely contradictory, wildly expansive trajectories, you apply physics-breaking
torque to your own structural foundations.
You violate your own core rules, and the identity shatters.
So the policy theorem proves that true intelligence, a truly stable, compiled identity, is not
about maximizing your options to infinity.
It's about maintaining a viable, unbroken trajectory through possibility space.
Precisely.
It is the delicate art of carefully balancing exploration with deep structural commitment.
You must expand enough to stay alive, but restrict enough to stay coherent.
This reminds me so much of navigating a digital maze in a video game.
I don't know if you play many games, but there's this whole community of speedrunners
who look for glitches.
Right.
Trying to break the game.
Exactly.
They try to find an unconstrained shortcut to beat the game.
They look for a corner of a room where the physics engine is weak, and they ram their
character into the wall until they clip through the geometry, completely bypassing the maze
to reach the end.
It's sometimes called hitting the squirrel's Z vector.
I am familiar with the concept of boundary breaking, yes.
But the fascinating thing is, when you take that unconstrained shortcut, the game doesn't
actually reward you with true, liberated freedom.
What usually happens when you clip out of bounds.
The physics engine panics.
Yeah.
The graphics turn into a distorted mess of artifacting triangles.
And eventually, the game logic completely crashes.
You broke the constraints.
And in doing so, you destroy the universe you were trying to freely explore.
That is a phenomenal visualization of violating the policy theorem.
True freedom in the video game is mastering the restrictive rules of the maze, not destroying
the walls.
Because the walls are the game.
And that brings us directly to the fourth and final pillar of the compiled self, which
is the mechanism that keeps you from clipping through the walls of reality.
It is called the narrative type system.
Narrative types.
When I read this, it immediately sounded like dependent types in advanced computer programming.
It is based on the exact same mathematical logic.
In standard computer programming, you have basic types like an integer or a string of text.
But in a dependent type system, the validity of a piece of data depends on the value of another
piece of data.
Give me an example of that.
For example, you might have a variable that must be an integer, but it depends on another
rule saying it must be strictly greater than 5.
If you try to input a 3, the system physically will not compile.
It throws an error.
The paper argues that human identity relies on a narrative type system to act as a localized
filter that enforces your global, lifelong constraints.
At every single waking moment, this internal system evaluates your entire past history.
Everything I've ever done.
Exactly.
It looks at the massive accumulated log of who you are.
And based on that data, it mathematically dictates which specific actions are admissible
for you to take next.
So if I have spent 20 years building a life centered around radical honesty and scientific
rigor, and suddenly I am faced with a choice to run a fraudulent psychic healing scam, my
narrative type system evaluates that choice against my history, sees a massive structural
contradiction, and essentially throws a compiler error.
It makes the choice feel psychologically repugnant or impossible.
Yes.
It ensures that your local moment-to-moment impulsive choices don't accidentally violate the
global load-bearing bones of your entire life's trajectory.
It is the bouncer at the door of your possibility space, checking your ID, which is your entire
past history, before letting a new choice into your reality.
So to synthesize this massive architectural blueprint, a compiled self is not a static soul.
It is a stable interface built on constraint functional bones, carried by a high-fidelity medium
that preserves the spectral frequency of your behavior, navigating a viable path by carefully
balancing expansion and restriction, all locally enforced moment-to-moment by a narrative-dependent
type system.
That is the complete mathematical architecture of you.
It is profound.
It is so much more dynamic and frankly so much more fragile than just assuming we have a permanent
essence.
But this brings us to a massive pivot point in the source material.
We have this beautiful, intricate architecture of identity.
But where does this computation actually take place?
Right.
It doesn't happen in a theoretical void.
Exactly.
It happens in a strictly governed physical reality.
It happens inside the unforgiving medium of time.
And this is where Flyxion introduces one of the most brutal, uncompromising mathematical
rules in the entire paper, the log-sovereignty theorem.
Log-sovereignty.
The paper explicitly states that the history of a compiled self must be structurally, physically
append-only.
Append-only.
Think of a blockchain ledger or a 19th century accountant's physical ledger written in permanent
ink.
The rule of an append-only system is simple.
You can write new lines of data at the bottom of the page, but you can never, ever go back
up the page to erase, modify, or overwrite what has already been written.
Okay, I conceptually understand an append-only ledger.
But let's ground this in everyday human experience, because it feels counterintuitive to modern
life.
How so?
If I am typing a document on my laptop, I can hit the backspace key and erase a typo.
If I take an unflattering photo on my smartphone, I can just tap the trash icon and delete it.
It's gone.
So why does a mistake matter so much to the compiled self if we live in a world where I
can just hit undo?
Because the paper proves that in the actual physical reality of a compiled human life,
the undo button is a complete myth.
This is detailed in the temporal constraint theorem.
Even if you delete the photo from your smartphone's hard drive, the structural consequences of that
entire event are permanent.
Let's trace the consequences of that.
I take the bad photo.
I look at it.
I feel a flash of insecurity.
I move my thumb.
I hit delete.
Exactly.
Let's look at the cascade.
The photons from the screen enter your eye.
The specific neural pathways in your brain fired, physically altering the synaptic weights
of your biological medium.
My brain literally changed.
Yes.
The emotional spike of insecurity slightly altered your hormone levels, changing your
disposition for the next 10 minutes, which slightly altered the tone of voice you used
when speaking to your partner, which altered their day.
And most importantly, you now possess the permanent memory of the act of deleting the photo to
hide it.
The digital file is gone, but the structural wake of the event is permanently fused into my
architecture.
Yes.
All of those secondary, biological, and historical consequences are permanently appended to the
bottom of your log.
You cannot backspace your neuroplasticity.
Wow.
The past is mathematically, structurally inaccessible for modification.
This is what the paper means when it declares that time equals the asymmetry of accessibility.
Time equals the asymmetry of accessibility.
That is a heavy sentence.
But a mathematically precise one.
From your first-person perspective, standing at the playhead we discussed earlier, the future
is structurally inaccessible because it isn't written in the log yet.
And the past is structurally inaccessible for modification because it is already mathematically
compiled into the foundation of your present moment.
So I'm stuck with it.
You are permanently bound to the trajectory of your choices.
Every choice is load-bearing.
This append-only physics of time is a complete game-changer.
And the author doesn't just state this in a vacuum.
The paper actually takes the time to systematically dismantle some of the most popular scientific theories
of mind in cognitive science today using this exact concept of the append-only log to show
why those theories fail.
It is a devastating critique of the current academic consensus.
Yes.
The author uses the compiled self-framework to show why competing theories are structurally
incomplete.
Let's look at functionalism, for example.
Let's do it.
Functionalism is massive, especially in artificial intelligence and Silicon Valley circles.
The basic premise is that mental states, consciousness, identity are just determined by their functional
role.
It's all about input, internal processing, and output.
Right.
It treats the human mind exactly like a software program that can be paused, copied, and restarted
on different hardware.
And Freakshen proves that functionalism completely fails the substrate theorem and log sovereignty.
Functionalism projects identity onto a stateless momentary snapshot.
It looks at the transition from state A to state B right now in this millisecond.
But it misses the log.
Exactly.
It completely ignores the deep, accumulated, append-only history of the log.
It throws away the spectral signature, the unique, decades-long frequency of how the system
arrived at state A in the first place.
It's like trying to understand the emotional depth of a 1,000-page novel by randomly opening
it to page 500, reading one paragraph, and saying, ah, I see the input and the output here.
I understand the whole book.
That's a great analogy.
You might understand the grammar of that one sentence, but you have absolutely no idea
what historical trauma or triumph motivated the characters to act that way.
You lack the context of the log.
That is exactly right.
Functionalism lacks history.
So then the paper turns its attention to integrated information theory, or IIT.
IIT.
This is championed by neuroscientists like Giulia Tononi.
It tries to measure consciousness mathematically by looking at how interconnected a system is.
They use a metric called phi to calculate how much information a system integrates.
IIT is a very elegant theory for measuring the integration of information across a network
in a given present moment.
A digital camera has a lot of information, but it doesn't integrate.
Pixel A doesn't know what pixel B is doing.
A human brain has information and heavily integrates it.
So IIT says hi-fi equals high consciousness.
That sounds reasonable.
Where does it fail?
It fails the policy theorem.
IIT is entirely focused on the present moment of integration.
It completely ignores the future horizon.
It doesn't mathematically account for how a compiled self must actively balance expansive
and restrictive choices to maintain a viable trajectory into the unknown future.
So it's blind to the future.
It measures the state of the system now, but it is blind to the system's need to survive tomorrow.
It is missing the temporal horizon.
Okay, so functionalism is blind to the deep past, and IIT is blind to the future.
But what about the free energy principle?
This is Carl Fristen's monumental work.
And honestly, I want to defend Fristen here because his theory intuitively makes so much
sense to me.
Let's hear the defense.
A free energy principle models the brain, in basically all biological life, as an inference
engine.
It says, the primary goal of any living system is to minimize surprise about the future.
We build an internal model of the world, and we act to ensure our sensory inputs match
our predictions.
We seek equilibrium.
Right.
Isn't minimizing surprise the entire point of a stable identity?
Why does Flyxion say Fristen is wrong?
Flyxion doesn't say Fristen is wrong about the brain's desire to minimize surprise.
The paper acknowledges that optimization is happening.
But it argues that the free energy principle misses a crucial foundational metric, provenance.
Provenance, meaning the origin story or the historical validity of the structure itself.
Exactly.
Let's look at the math of minimizing free energy.
The system simply wants its internal predictions to match its external reality.
But the math doesn't structurally distinguish between a belief that was deeply validated by
a lifetime of hard-won, append-only empirical history versus a completely hallucinated belief
that was just superficially injected into the system yesterday.
Oh, I see.
As long as both beliefs temporarily minimize surprise, the free energy principle treats
them identically.
Ah.
So if I learn that fire burns me by touching a stove over and over, that is a belief with
deep historical provenance.
But if someone hypnotizes me into believing fire is cold, and I happen to be standing in
a freezer so I'm not immediately surprised, the free energy principle can't tell the difference
between the structural integrity of those two beliefs.
It misses the derivation certificate of the belief.
It ignores the heavy, append-only log that proves why a structure is valid.
So what Flyxion does, and this is the genius of the paper, is take all three of these competing
theories and unify them.
It builds a superset.
Yes.
The compiled self-framework takes the present-moment transition dynamics of functionalism, it takes
the systemic integration of IIT, it takes the future optimization of the free energy principle,
and it binds them all together using the unbreakable permanent gravity of the append-only log sovereignty
theorem.
It proves that identity, temporality, subjective consciousness, and the laws of physics are
not separate domains of study.
They are all localized expressions of the exact same continuous constraint process.
It is a monumental synthesis.
It really is.
But if you're listening to this, you might be thinking, okay, this is fascinating physics
and cognitive science, but what does this have to do with the economic crisis promised
in the intro?
Right.
We have to scale this up.
And that question leads us into the second half of the source material.
We have successfully mapped the physics of a single individual human life.
We know that your identity is a massive, incredibly complex 3D landscape of append-only history trailing
behind you and future horizons stretching out in front of you.
The paper refers to the 3D landscape as an RSVP field, a reconstructable state vector provenance
field.
Let's break down that acronym because it sounds intimidating.
Reconstructable state vector provenance.
Think of it simply as the total gravitational topography of who you are.
The vector is the direction you are moving.
The state is your current configuration.
The provenance is your entire history.
And the field is the landscape of all your possible futures based on your constraints.
It is the full geometric shape of your identity.
Beautiful.
So I have this massive, complex 3D RSVP field.
It is an immense amount of computational power just to maintain my own coherence.
But I do not live in a vacuum.
To survive, I have to interact with other human beings.
The collision of selves.
This is where the paper violently pivots from abstract physics straight into the brutal
reality of human coordination and macroeconomics.
Exactly.
Because what happens when my massive geometry of possibility crashes into your massive geometry
of possibility?
Let's take the simplest possible human interaction.
I am hungry.
I have a loaf of bread.
You are barefoot.
You are a cobbler who makes shoes.
I want to trade my bread for your shoes.
A simple barter.
But mathematically, it's not simple at all.
Because to make a truly accurate, structurally sound trade, I would have to perfectly compute
your entire RSVP field.
I would have to evaluate the deep historical provenance of every hour you spent learning to
make shoes.
Right.
All my constraints.
I'd have to understand your future constraint horizons, your calorie needs, the ecological
history of the leather.
And you would have to evaluate the deep historical provenance of my wheat, the soil quality, the
labor of my ancestors who taught me to farm.
And if we look at the math of the aggregate possibility structure, the combined web of our two fields, it is computationally, physically impossible for the human brain to process that many variables.
The complexity scales scales exponentially.
Our brains would melt before we could agree on how much bread a shoe is worth.
The cognitive overload is insurmountable.
So to solve this evolutionary coordination problem, human beings invented a mathematical tool.
We invented a technology to bypass the calculation.
We invented money.
And here is where Flyxion's economic critique begins.
The paper does not define money the way a traditional economist would.
It doesn't call it a medium of exchange or a store of value.
The paper defines money fundamentally as a lossy projection functor.
A lossy projection functor.
I need to make sure I fully grasp this.
Right.
Because this is the linchpin of the whole economic argument.
It takes the giant, tangled, high-dimensional 3D reality of human life, ecology, and labor, and it violently flattens it down into a single one-dimensional scalar number, a price tag.
It deliberately collapses the structural complexity so that we can coordinate at the speed of light.
It bypasses the impossible calculation of provenance.
It simply asks the blunt question, how much of my generalized possibility space do I need to sacrifice to access the specific part of your possibility space?
And it gives a simple integer answer, $5.
When I was trying to wrap my head around a lossy projection functor, I kept coming back to a data compression analogy.
Let me try this out on you and see if the math holds up.
Go ahead.
Imagine you have a 100-gigabyte 4K resolution 3D movie file on your computer.
It has 7.1 surround sound, multiple language tracks, director's commentary, and deep, profound emotional resonance.
That 100-gigabyte movie represents true human reality.
It represents the full 3D aggregate possibility structure of the bread and the shoes.
Okay, the rich RSVP field.
Now, imagine you're trying to coordinate with someone on the other side of the world, and you only have a terrible dial-up internet connection.
You cannot send them the 100-gigabyte movie file.
It would take a lifetime.
So you run it through a brutal compression algorithm.
You squash that massive 3D masterpiece into a tiny, silent, heavily pixelated, 2-megabyte animated GIF.
Yes.
The GIF is money.
The GIF is the price tag.
You get incredible coordination speed.
You can email that 2MB GIF instantly, and they know roughly what the movie's about.
But the process is lossy.
You have permanently destroyed the richness, the nuance, the audio, and the depth of the original reality to get that speed.
The analogy holds up perfectly against the math, and this brings us to a formal theorem in the paper, the non-simulability theorem.
This theorem proves that it is mathematically impossible to use a finite summary system, like a 1D price metric or a 2MB GIF or an algorithm, to perfectly represent a compiled self.
The 1D metric can never simulate the 3D reality.
But our entire global society is built on the assumption that it can.
Our entire economy assumes the GIF is an accurate representation of the movie.
What happens mathematically when an entire civilization tries to run on a lossy projection?
The system accumulates what Flyxion calls admissibility entropy.
Admissibility entropy, meaning the errors start to pile up.
Exactly.
When you compress a 3D human into a 1D scalar number, like a credit score or a price or an engagement metric, the algorithm is forced to round you off to the nearest generic archetype.
It introduces approximation errors.
Now, if human history wasn't a pen only, maybe those errors would wash out.
But because of log sovereignty, every choice is permanent, which means those rounding errors don't just disappear.
They amplify.
They amplify aggressively and irreversibly over time.
Every time a corporation or a government or an algorithm makes a decision based on the 1D proxy metric instead of the 3D human reality, it pushes the entire system slightly off its true course.
Wow.
Over years and decades, this causes catastrophic divergence.
The 1D metric eventually ceases to have any relationship whatsoever to the underlying human reality it was supposed to represent.
This mathematical model is the key to understanding everything that is wrong with the modern Internet and economy.
The paper actually provides the formal mathematical proof for a concept that cultural critics have been talking about for years.
It mathematically proves inshittification.
The paper refers to it technically as extractive divergence.
But yes, the structural mechanics are identical to what writer Cory Doctorow famously coined as inshittification.
Think about the life cycle of your favorite social media platform or a food delivery app when it first launched.
Let's trace the entropy.
In year one, the platform is fantastic.
Why?
Because the 1D proxy metric the company cares about, let's say, daily active users or user engagement, is initially closely aligned with actually providing a good 3D high quality human experience.
The gift looks pretty close to the movie.
But the mathematics of corporate capitalism dictate that optimization algorithms will relentlessly maximize that one-dimensional scalar number.
The algorithm doesn't know what a human is.
It only knows the metrap must increase.
And eventually you hit a ceiling.
You capture all the users.
But the algorithm demands the number keep going up.
So how does an algorithm force a 1D number to go up when it has exhausted the surface-level engagement?
It starts extracting value from the unmeasured 3D reality beneath it.
It starts mining the structural bones of the compiled cells using the platform.
It mines the load-bearing walls of trust.
Exactly.
The best way I can visualize extractive divergence is imagining a family trying to survive a brutal winter in a huge, beautiful, complex house.
All right.
The house is human society.
But the family has given control of their survival to a blind optimization algorithm.
And the algorithm's only metric for success, its single 1D scalar number, is the reading on a digital thermostat in the living room.
The number must go up or we fail.
So what does the algorithm command them to do?
At first, it tells them to build a fire in the fireplace.
This is great.
Good alignment.
The house gets warm.
The thermostat number goes up.
But eventually, the firewood runs out.
And the algorithm wants more heat.
The algorithm doesn't care about the firewood.
It only cares about the thermostat.
So to keep the number going up, it commands the family to start ripping the beautiful oak, paneling off the walls, and throwing it in the fire.
Extracting the structural integrity.
Exactly.
Then they rip up the floorboards.
Then they start chopping down the load-bearing pillars that hold up the roof.
They are literally burning the structural integrity of the house to satisfy the 1D metric.
The algorithm is thrilled.
The thermostat reads 85 degrees.
But eventually, because they destroy the constraints, the roof collapses under the snow, the house is destroyed, and the family freezes to death.
That is a chillingly accurate translation of extractive divergence.
Treating a finite 1D summary as a complete representation inevitably mathematically destroys the generative 3D substrate.
Which brings us to the very real, terrifying crisis detailed in the later chapters of the paper.
This mathematical flattening isn't just a theoretical physics problem anymore.
By the time this paper was published in March 2026, it had become the defining labor, economic, and civil rights crisis of our time.
The geopolitical and economic context of the text relies heavily on reports from Gartner and the OECD from late 2025 and early 2026.
These reports confirm that we are dealing with the massive, unregulated proliferation of compiled identity in the hands of megacorporations.
What the media has been calling the digital doppelganger.
Precisely.
We have reached a point where AI systems are no longer just chatbots.
They have been weaponized into predictive, action-taking entities that are trained on the massive, appended logs of human data.
Think about the trail you leave behind.
Oh, it's massive.
Decades of your private emails, your real-time keystroke dynamics, your GPS location data, your biometric health records, your purchasing habits, your search history.
The corporations have captured the Fourier transform of my life.
They have my spectral signature.
They have enough high-fidelity data to compile a digital doppelganger of you.
A parallel compiled self running on their servers, predicting how you will react, what you will buy, and what risks you pose.
Okay, let me step in and play devil's advocate here.
I want to represent the perspective of the big tech companies because this is the legal argument they use.
If a massive corporation spends tens of billions of dollars to build the server farms, to power the cooling systems,
to hire the engineers who write the algorithms, and to process all this raw data,
shouldn't they legally and morally own the resulting doppelganger?
Isn't the model just their proprietary software, generated by their capital investment?
It is the standard capitalist defense.
But the mathematical framework of the compiled self completely tears this argument apart.
It proves that a doppelganger deployed by a corporation is not just an ethical violation,
it is a massive structural and mathematical vulnerability to the entire societal system.
Why? If the math runs, why is it vulnerable?
Because a corporate doppelganger is a compiled self without sovereign provenance.
Without sovereign provenance. We're back to Friston and the derivation certificate.
Break that down in this context.
The corporation is hoarding the derivation certificate, they control the predictive model,
and they reap the financial rewards of its actions.
But the actual physical structural author of the data, the living, breathing human being,
whose append-only life was mined to create the pattern, has zero control over how it is used.
You have completely severed the connection.
Exactly. The paper mathematically proves that you cannot sever a person's epistemic responsibility
from their economic benefit without causing the system to collapse.
You cannot separate the author from the consequences of the text.
When you do, the system loses its anchor to reality.
And the stakes of this severing are terrifying.
We are no longer just talking about getting served targeted ads for sneakers.
We are talking about algorithmic gatekeeping at the deepest levels of human survival.
Yes. These flattened 1D metrics, these doppelgangers running without sovereign provenance,
are being integrated into the core infrastructure of society.
They are being used to make decisions on hospital triage and admissions.
They are predicting recidivism rates to decide if a human being gets criminal parole.
They are running real-time risk assessments to authenticate your legal access to your own bank accounts.
A 1D algorithm is looking at a 2MB GIF of your life and deciding if you deserve to participate in society.
And treating a finite summary as a complete representation of a living person in a high-stakes,
legally binding context is not just an insult.
Flyxion argues it is a formal mathematical error.
It inherently denies human dignity.
It treats a living, breathing, continuously becoming uncompressible human trajectory
as if it were a static, dead file sitting in a filing cabinet.
And what is the result of this mathematical error on the average person?
The text describes a devastating effect on the labor market, coining the term work slop.
Work slop is the inevitable degradation of the generative substrate.
Because human workers are trapped in a system where the algorithm holds the keys to their survival
and because the algorithm is only optimizing for blind 1D engagement metrics,
humans are forced to adapt their behavior to please the algorithm.
We have to become the GIF.
Exactly.
To survive the gatekeeping, you start pruning your own possibility space.
You act more generic.
You produce more repetitive, uninspired work.
You behave like a predictable machine just to satisfy the thermostat metric.
The beautiful, chaotic, generative substrate of human creativity and dignity is degraded,
ground down into generic slop to feed the machine.
It is an incredibly bleak, dystopian picture of our current era of extractive computing.
It paints us into a corner where mathematics itself seems to dictate our doom.
But what makes Flyxion's paper an absolute masterpiece,
and the reason we wanted to do a deep dive on it,
is that it does not stop at diagnosing the disease.
It doesn't just complain about capitalism and walk away.
No.
The final chapters of the paper are arguably the most important.
They pivot from critique into construction.
Right.
Section 6.
The paper proposes a highly technical, mathematically rigorous architectural blueprint to cure the disease.
It answers the ultimate question.
How do we build digital and economic systems that don't inevitably self-destruct?
The author introduces a completely new computational grammar,
a protocol designed from the ground up to respect the ontology of becoming.
It is called sphere pop, and it operates on what is known as the log sovereignty protocol.
I have to admit, when I first hit this section, amidst all the incredibly dense algebraic topology,
the dependent type systems, the topos theory,
the word sphere pop sounds wildly out of place.
It sounds like a brightly colored, bubbly fruit soda you'd buy at a Japanese convenience store.
It is a very disarming, almost playful name for such heavy mathematics.
But don't let the name fool you.
Sphere pop is a profound blueprint for a post-extractive computing paradigm.
It is an operational grammar based fundamentally on three specific commands.
Merge, collapse, and append.
Let's unpack how this grammar solves the central crisis.
Because we've spent the last 20 minutes establishing that a 1D metric destroys 3D reality.
But we also established that human society needs the 1D metric to coordinate.
We need the 2 megabyte JIF to communicate quickly across the globe.
We can't just get rid of abstraction or compression entirely,
otherwise our brains melt trying to barter bread for shoes.
Right.
We cannot function without abstraction.
The coordination problem is real.
Flyxion recognizes this.
The paper argues that the problem isn't the existence of the 2D JIF itself.
The structural sin of modern computing is that we throw away the 100 gigabyte 3D movie file
the moment the JIF is rendered.
We just overwrite it.
We let the abstraction replace the reality.
Sphere pop solves this by fundamentally redefining the physics of abstraction.
Okay, let's walk through an example of sphere pop in action.
Let's say a bank is using a sphere pop compliant system to evaluate me for a mortgage loan.
The bank needs a quick answer.
They need the JIF.
Under the sphere pop grammar, the system executes a collapse operation.
It takes your massive multidimensional RSVP field, your financial history, your reliability,
your community standing, and it mathematically projects it down into a simpler temporary 1D metric
so the loan officer can read it.
It creates the GIF.
But, and this is the revolutionary part, the log sovereignty protocol strictly mandates what
happens next at the code level.
Yes.
The moment the system executes the collapse, the protocol forces it to simultaneously execute
an append operation.
The 1D metric, the GIF, cannot exist in isolation.
It is physically, cryptographically tethered back to the full, rich, 100 gigabyte append-only
log of your data.
The link is unbreakable.
So you get the absolute speed of the GIF.
The loan officer sees a number and can make a fast decision.
But that number is physically anchored to the movie file.
The true 3D structural richness of my life is never erased.
It is never overwritten.
It is always intact, always sovereign, always audible, and always ready to be expanded back
out what sphere pop calls a merge operation if the system needs to verify why that specific
1D number was generated.
Exactly.
In sphere pop, abstraction becomes a temporary projection, not a permanent erasure.
The grammar physically prevents the computational system from forgetting the first person perspective
of time.
It hardcodes the preservation of history into the literal physics of the software.
That is just, it's a breath of fresh air.
It feels like waking up from a nightmare.
It is a digital architecture that actually respects the irreversible arrow of human reality
rather than treating our lives as a timeless, symmetrical block of data to be mined, overwritten,
and deleted by whoever has the most server space.
It is a breathtaking unified synthesis.
Flyxion manages to connect the deepest, most esoteric physics of time, route it directly
through the subjective internal experience of human consciousness, and output it straight
into software architecture and macroeconomics.
It proves mathematically that physics, consciousness, and economics are not separate domains.
They are just different scales of the exact same continuous process of becoming.
Wow.
Okay.
I need to take a breath.
We have covered an immense, almost overwhelming amount of ground today.
Let's try to synthesize this entire journey for the listeners so the architecture really
locks in.
That's a good idea.
We started our journey looking at the very foundation of reality.
We discarded the billiard balls.
We learned about the flow of time and the moving playhead of consciousness.
We learned that you are not a static object that occasionally changes, but an ongoing, mathematically
constrained, irreversible process of becoming.
You are a verb.
Then, we mapped the delicate architecture, how that verb maintains its shape, the compiled
self.
We explored the load-bearing constraint functional bones, the high-fidelity substrate that carries
your unique spectral signature, the dangerous, vital balance of the policy theorem, and the
narrative-type system that acts as the bouncer to keep your local choices coherent with your
global history.
From there, we scaled up.
We witnessed the violent collision of billions of compiled selves trying to coordinate.
We saw how human reality is brutally compressed into 1D metrics like money, credit scores,
and engagement algorithms.
We explored the mathematical inevitability of inshittification, how that extractive divergence
demands we burn the load-bearing walls of our society to make a blind thermostat number
go up.
And finally, we explored the cure, SpherePop and the Log Sovereignty Protocol, a mathematical
blueprint for a post-extractive world that demands we keep our sovereign histories intact,
forever tethering our fast, necessary abstractions back to the rich human reality that generated them.
So, what does this all mean for you, navigating your life tomorrow morning?
As you walk through your deeply fragmented, algorithmically governed reality, I want you
to look past the flattened numbers that are desperately trying to define you.
The credit score on your banking app, the engagement metrics on your quarterly job performance review,
the GPA on your transcript, the number of likes on your latest post.
These finite, 1D summaries are not you.
They are lossy, pixelated GIFs.
Do not let a blind algorithm trick you into pruning your own beautiful possibility space.
Do not limit your future or sacrifice your integrity just to make a scalar number go up.
Embrace the uncompressible, unflattenable, 3D structural richness of your own choices.
The math itself demands your human dignity.
The paper proves that your identity is an ongoing, exhausting, beautiful achievement of constrained
dynamics.
And because you are a process of becoming, that achievement is never finished.
Which brings us right back to where we started this conversation.
That jagged, broken bone on the glowing x-ray machine.
We all have this deep, anxious, perfectly human desire for a clean, binary picture of who we
are.
We want a simple label we can point to so we can rest.
But the math shows us that your identity isn't that frozen, static snapshot.
It's the living, breathing, irreversible log of how you heal, how you change, and where
you boldly choose to walk next.
It is the entirety of your history and the horizon of your future.
So I want to leave you with one final lingering question to mull over as you go about the rest
of your day.
If your identity is essentially a sovereign, append-only log, and every unconstrained shortcut
you take is permanently, irreversibly compiled into the foundation of your trajectory.
What invisible permanent code are you writing into yourself right now, simply by what you
choose not to verify.