You almost certainly know this feeling.
I mean, I think anyone who spends any time online does.
It happens when you're watching, you know, incredibly intelligent people trying to analyze a totally broken online system.
Right. From inside that exact same system.
Exactly. From inside the system.
So you're watching this brilliant, highly produced video essay, or maybe you're listening to a deeply researched audio show,
and the creators are just perfectly naming all the problems of our digital discourse.
Oh, yeah. They point out the echo chambers. They completely diagnose the outrage cycles.
Yeah. They dismantle the shallow takes, like piece by piece. And then inevitably they propose these fixes.
And yet those fixes just they dissolve the absolute second they hit the air. Like the conversation just circles back on itself.
It's wild. The analysis is sharp. The people involved are, you know, really perceptive.
But the effort never actually touches the mechanism that's producing the situation in the first place.
Yeah. It doesn't touch the gears.
It really feels like watching someone try to bail water out of a sinking boat using a bucket that is literally made out of the exact same water.
We're calling it the feeling of absurdity.
That ambient exhaustion.
Yes. That ambient exhaustion that just comes from the suspicion that, you know, the harder we try to communicate complex ideas on these digital platforms,
the more those ideas just completely slip through our fingers.
Which is incredibly frustrating.
It is.
So today for this deep dive, we are going to explore why that feeling of a fragmented, chaotic digital world is not actually a failure of human intelligence.
Right. It's not a bug in our brains.
No, it isn't because we aren't smart enough or because the creators we watch aren't like researching hard enough.
It is a structural mathematical necessity of the platforms we use.
And to really understand this, we are pulling from a totally fascinating, honestly, incredibly dense paper.
It was published in 2026 by an author writing under the name Flyxion.
Flyxion. Yeah.
The paper is titled Selection Without Closure.
And what makes this text so remarkable is that it takes these rigorous tools of, you know, dynamical systems, mathematical modeling, topology.
Heavy stuff.
Very heavy stuff.
And it applies them directly to the messy, completely unquantifiable or silly thought world of online discourse.
So we are going to look at how feed-based platforms, like literally just the endless scroll on your phone, are systematically eliminating a very specific property of human language.
Yeah.
We'll uncover why the entire influencer class is currently trapped in this inescapable loop.
And perhaps most alarming, we'll see how this exact same mathematical dynamic is currently bleeding into artificial intelligence.
And the very way we build software itself.
Which is terrifying.
But before we get to the AI stuff, the paper uses a really helpful framing device early on to illustrate this feeling of absurdity.
Right.
The video essayist example.
Yeah.
Flyxion describes this sophisticated video essayist who is dissecting the dominance of highly polarized political content in algorithmic feeds.
Like the essayist is trying to figure out why certain political factions just totally dominate the space.
And why counter strategies always seem to fail.
Right.
And it is super crucial to note here, for you listening, Flyxion is absolutely not taking a political side in this analysis.
And, you know, neither are we.
No.
Not really.
Whether a creator is trying to boost a left-wing perspective or a right-wing perspective or literally anything in between, the paper's observation remains exactly identical.
Because the observation is that all of these creators, regardless of their politics, are treating the platform as a neutral channel.
Yes.
They ask, how do we send our specific political signals better?
What they completely fail to ask, and what Flyxion's math basically demands that we ask, is how the channel itself fundamentally transforms the signal.
Exactly.
It isn't about the politics of the content at all.
It is strictly about the physics of the medium.
The physics of the medium.
I love that phrasing.
So let's unpack that.
Because that assumption of a neutral channel is really the foundational error we all make.
We do.
I mean, we all assume that digital feeds just select for engagement.
We use that word constantly.
Oh, all the time.
Engagement is the buzzword.
Right.
We assume the dashboard metrics, clicks, watch time, likes, all of that are the underlying reality of the system.
But Flyxion just completely pulls that assumption apart.
Engagement is just the symptom.
It's the readout.
Exactly.
It's merely the readout on the thermometer.
It's not the heat itself.
So if engagement is just the symptom, what is the actual formal property generating that symptom?
The paper defines it as recomposability.
Recomposability.
Okay, let's drill into that.
So recomposability is the capacity of a piece of content to be completely detached from its original context,
injected into a totally new context, and recirculated without losing its effective charge.
And by effective charge, we're talking about its emotional payload, right?
Exactly.
Its ability to generate an instant reaction, whether that's validation or anger or just amusement.
So it's basically a measure of how easily an idea can be ripped out of its home, slapped somewhere else, and still do its job.
That's a great way to look at it.
Like, if a piece of content has really high recomposability, someone can just clip 10 seconds out of a two-hour lecture, right?
Drop it onto a short-form video platform next to, I don't know, a meme and a cooking tutorial.
And it still hits the viewer just as hard.
Yeah.
The viewer doesn't need to know who the speaker is or what the broader lecture was even about.
The emotional reaction is triggered before the intellectual processing even begins.
And that immediate, totally context-free trigger is the engine of propagation.
Yeah.
The platform's algorithms naturally elevate whatever propagates the fastest.
Which means the platform heavily, heavily selects for high recomposability.
Yes.
But Flyxion also sets up this diametric opposite to that force.
If recomposability is the ability to be detached, the opposing mathematical force is what the paper calls binding force.
Binding force.
Okay.
Let's define that for the listener.
Binding force is the capacity of an idea to remain identical to itself across different contexts.
It is basically the mechanism by which language enforces semantic identity.
To see this clearly, I think looking at the extremes helps.
Oh, for sure.
So, on the absolute maximum end of binding force, you have something like a formal mathematical proof.
Right.
A proof means the exact same thing, whether you are reading it in a dusty textbook from 1950 or on a digital tablet tomorrow.
Because the conclusion is strictly bound to the premises.
Exactly.
You cannot just clip line four of the Pythagorean theorem derivation, completely detach it from the rest of the proof, and apply it to, like, a debate about healthcare policy.
I mean, you could try, but it won't work.
It would be nonsense.
It would be immediately recognized as an error.
Just a complete non-sequitur.
It absolutely requires its entire structural context to exist.
And then, on the absolute minimum end of binding force, you have something like a political slogan.
Oh.
A slogan has almost zero binding because you can clip it, you can paint it on a cardboard sign, you can put it in a highly produced video, apply it to a dozen totally disparate geopolitical conflicts.
And it still functions perfectly.
Yes.
It retains its effective charge while happily conforming to whatever new context you drop it into.
Okay.
So the paper introduces this mathematical function to describe how algorithms filter these properties.
Flyxion calls it the platform selection equation, DL platform.
Great.
And what DL platform demonstrates mathematically is that platforms systematically penalize binding force.
Okay.
I want to try an analogy here to see if the causal mechanism of J platform makes sense.
Go for it.
Let's say recomposability, like the political slogan, is like a single standard Lego brick.
You can take that one red Lego brick and snap it onto a toy spaceship.
Or you can pull off and snap it onto a medieval castle.
It fits everywhere.
Right.
It does its job everywhere because its interface is universally adaptable.
It requires very little from its surrounding environment.
That maps perfectly to high recomposability.
Awesome.
So then binding force, the mathematical proof, is more like a highly specialized, intricately
machined engine block for a Formula One car.
Oh, I like this.
It is incredibly complex and it is deeply meaningful in its specific context.
Like it generates immense power.
But if you try to take that engine block out and shove it into a Honda Civic, it just sits there.
It physically cannot interface with the Civic's transmission.
Exactly.
It only works in the exact environment it was engineered for.
The engine block is constrained by its own structure.
It has high binding force.
And the really important thing to understand here is the reason day platform penalizes the
engine block.
Right.
It isn't because the algorithm hates difficulty or because users are inherently lazy.
Which is what everyone always says.
Oh, attention spans are shrinking.
Right.
That's a super common psychological critique.
But Flyxion completely rejects it.
The feed doesn't hate intelligence.
The feed hates accountability.
Accountability is the key variable there.
Let's dig into that.
Well, the engine block is accountable to its design.
If a single valve is machined incorrectly, you know, immediately because the engine just
fails to start.
Yeah.
Content with high binding force, like a carefully qualified philosophical argument or a tightly
defined legal concept, can be proven wrong.
It makes a claim that can be checked, tested, and found to fail structurally.
It demands semantic precision.
And the feed algorithm suppresses this kind of accountability because precision actively
resists being quoted out of context.
Exactly.
If an argument means something so incredibly specific that it can't be easily reshared by
someone who wants to use it for their own, you know, slightly different agenda, its propagation
potential basically drops to zero.
The system requires fluidity.
Yes.
Viral propagation inherently requires millions of people projecting their own personal meanings
onto a single artifact.
If an artifact is tightly bound to its original meaning, it rejects those projections.
Wow.
So recomposability and binding force operate as strict inverse properties.
Any operation you perform on an idea to increase its ability to be reshared out of context
mathematically decreases its binding force.
Every single time.
Which, you know, brings us back to that feeling of exhaustion we talked about at the start.
Like absurdity.
Right.
When you open your phone and feel totally overwhelmed by the sea of fragmented shouting
where nuance seems totally dead, it is not because human attention spans are magically
shrinking.
You are living inside an architectural structure that mathematically penalizes coherent, accountable
thought.
You are swimming in an ocean of Lego bricks because the water is highly acidic to engine blocks.
Oh, that's good.
It's the necessary mechanism by which engagement is actually produced.
But this introduces a massive structural contradiction that Flyxion spends the next section of the
paper trying to resolve.
Yes.
The long form content problem.
Right.
If the system is so heavily rigged against the heavy, difficult engine block, how do we
explain the explosive popularity of long form, supposedly difficult content?
Because it's everywhere.
It is.
We see three-hour philosophical podcasts, these massive multi-part video essays on like super
niche historical topics.
We see dense sub-stack articles going mega viral all the time.
Right.
And on the surface, a three-hour deep dive into the history of zoning laws seems to have
incredible binding force.
It's long.
It's difficult.
It uses really large vocabularies.
It seems to directly violate the idea that the feed only wants Lego bricks.
It does seem that way.
But Flyxion anticipates this objection.
The paper argues that the strategies used by the influencer class producing this content
are not actually rebellious or subversive.
They aren't beating the algorithm.
Right.
They are exhibiting what the paper calls convergence under selection.
Convergence under selection, which implies they have adapted to the environment, not conquered
it.
Precisely.
The creator might present themselves as this rogue intellectual surviving in a degraded
wasteland, but they are actually just utilizing very specific adaptation tactics.
And the paper outlines three primary tactics, right?
Yes.
First is aestheticizing.
Creators embed complex political or philosophical ideas into really high production visual formats.
Cinematic lighting, dynamic editing, carefully curated soundtracks.
Second is narrativizing.
Right.
They take abstract, non-linear arguments and forcefully cram them into character-driven stories
with traditional emotional arcs.
And the third is persona amplification.
They cultivate these really deep parasocial relationships with the audience, relying on
the audience's trust in the creator's identity to sort of carry the weight of the dense topic.
We see this constantly.
Like, a video analyzing an obscure piece of economic theory will be lit like a cyberpunk
film.
It'll feature a narrator drinking coffee by a rain streak window while a lo-fi beat plays
in the background.
It projects this overwhelming aura of depth.
Yeah.
The creator totally believes they are smuggling the complex engine block into the system by,
like, painting it red so it looks like a Lego brick.
But Flyxion drops a formal definition here that just dismantles this entirely.
The paper defines this phenomena as pseudobinding.
Pseudobinding.
Yes.
Pseudobinding is content that performs the aesthetic of rigor and depth.
The long run times, the moody music, the academic jargon, while remaining fundamentally highly
recomposable, the depth is literally a structural illusion.
Okay.
I struggle with the word illusion there, though.
I really do.
If the video is actually three hours long and it actually cites real academic texts,
how is the depth an illusion?
The words are physically present in the video.
Because the test is in the recomposability.
Apply the clipping test.
The clipping test.
Can you extract 20 seconds of that three-hour video essay posted on a short-form feed,
and does it retain its effective charge?
Oh, absolutely.
In fact, that is basically the primary marketing strategy for long-form content.
Creators will cut a highly provocative 30-second quote from their three-hour video,
overlay it onto a split screen with, I don't know, video game footage, and it goes incredibly viral.
And Flyxion's math points out a devastating structural truth about that.
If you can clip a 10-minute philosophical argument into 20 seconds without losing its emotional punch,
that implies its emotional punch was never dependent on its structural duration.
Wow.
It never possessed actual binding force.
Because true inferential arguments, where the conclusion physically requires the 10 minutes of prior logical development to make sense,
they can't be clipped without a complete loss of meaning.
Exactly.
But those truly bound arguments do not circulate on feeds, precisely because they fail the clipping test.
So pseudobinding is basically just wearing the clothing of an intellectual argument.
Underneath the cinematic lighting and the big words, the actual payload is still just highly recomposable emotion.
Yes.
It simulates constraint, but offers zero resistance to being ripped out of context.
And the platform algorithm aggressively selects for this because it's like the ultimate optimization.
It makes the user feel intelligent for consuming deep content, which drives up retention, while remaining fully atomizable and shareable, which drives up propagation.
But achieving this balance is incredibly labor-intensive.
And this brings us to the socioeconomic core of Flyxion's argument, which models what they call the privileged structure of digital discourse.
This part of the paper was fascinating.
The author introduces a variable, denoted as CPS-E wire, to mathematically model the production cost of any given content strategy.
Okay, let's break down that CPS equation.
How does Flyxion actually quantify production cost in this context?
The equation splits cost into two very distinct vectors.
True binding, creating a rigorous, logically airtight mathematical or philosophical proof, requires high intellectual cost.
It requires immense mental labor, isolation, and time spent purely on the logical architecture of the idea.
Simulating binding, however, producing pseudo-binding, requires high material cost.
Ah, it requires the expense of cameras, the editing teams, the lighting rigs.
Exactly.
It requires research assistance to scrape citations and the vast amount of free time necessary to orchestrate all of this production while still appearing perfectly casual and effortless on camera.
So the algorithm is fundamentally altering the economic requirements for participating in public discourse.
As the system demands more and more sophisticated forms of pseudo-binding to capture attention, the material cost of entry basically skyrockets.
Precisely.
The system structurally filters out anyone who cannot afford the material cover charge.
It filters out working class voices.
Yes.
Or simply individuals who just cannot sustain the massive financial and temporal costs of performing this constant cinematic adaptation.
Selection filters operate on populations over really long time horizons.
So as CPS increases, the visible practitioners in feed-optimized discourse disproportionately become those who have the existing capital to sustain high production adaptation without relying on that production for their immediate physical survival.
And the irony here is incredibly dark.
So dark.
These high production creators receive immense cultural capital for appearing to critique the shallow internet.
They are hailed as rogue public intellectuals fighting for nuance.
But mathematically, according to the CPS all function and the selection regime, they are actually feeding the system exactly the highly recomposable high engagement residue it hungers for.
They are not the resistance to the algorithm.
They are its premium product line.
It is the tragedy of convergence under selection.
They haven't bypassed the feed.
The feed has shaped them into the perfect, highly efficient providers of pseudobinding.
They are culturally rewarded for the appearance of thinking that binds while structurally producing content perfectly optimized for semantic drift.
Exactly.
I can hear a counter argument forming, though.
Let's examine the Trojan horse strategy because many creators explicitly state this is their methodology.
Oh, yes, the Trojan horse.
The rationale goes like this.
I know the system only rewards shallow engagement.
I know people just want to click on popular media.
So I will use a review of a massive blockbuster movie like, let's say, a Marvel film to sneak in a genuinely complex argument about existentialist philosophy.
People click for the superhero, but they end up staying for Sartre.
Isn't that a valid, subversive way to utilize the system's mechanics against itself?
Flyxion actually dedicates an entire section to dismantling this exact premise.
The paper labels it the Trojan horse fallacy.
Okay, why is it a fallacy?
To prove why it fails, the paper introduces a mathematical limit called the Trojan horse bound.
Let's unpack the mechanics of this Trojan horse bound.
Why does my totally brilliant superhero philosophy strategy fail to deliver the payload?
The bound dictates that when you translate a difficult, highly bound idea into a more accessible, highly recomposable form, the translation process inherently destroys the binding force.
Wait, inherently?
Yes.
You do not preserve the original idea.
You only preserve what Flyxion calls the recomposable residue.
Recomposable residue.
Okay, if I do a 40-minute video linking a superhero's character arc to Sartre's concept of radical freedom, what exactly is the residue and what gets destroyed?
Think about it this way.
A philosophical argument possesses binding force because its conclusion strictly depends on the rigid structure of its premises.
Step A logically necessitates step B, which necessitates step C.
Right.
The conclusion only possesses truth value within the context of that specific scaffolding.
When you translate that into commentary on a superhero movie, what actually survives the translation is just the conclusion.
Oh.
The emotional vibe of the conclusion survives, and it's heavily subsidized by the audience's pre-existing emotional attachment to the superhero.
I see.
So the audience feels the weight of the conclusion because they are watching a highly dramatic movie scene, not because they have actually tracked the logic.
Exactly.
The inferential path, the rigorous step-by-step logical scaffolding that actually proved the conclusion, is destroyed.
And it does not survive the translation because inferential structure is inherently non-recomposable.
Because you can't clip the middle step of a complex proof and make it go viral.
Right.
It is structurally meaningless on its own.
So the audience receives the profound-sounding philosophical conclusion, but they are entirely stripped of the cognitive tools required to test the idea, challenge it, or understand its boundaries.
They get the mic drop quote, but they don't get the mechanism.
And without the mechanism, the idea loses all accountability.
If the audience doesn't know the inferential path that leads to radical freedom, they don't know how to extend that idea to a totally new situation in their own lives.
Or, more dangerously, they have no way of realizing when the idea is being misapplied or manipulated by someone else.
It ceases to be philosophy and becomes a blunt aesthetic instrument.
Yeah.
That's, wow.
As Flyxion bluntly summarizes, this is not political or philosophical education.
It is aestheticization.
Yes.
The ideas that can be successfully smuggled inside accessible cultural forms are only the ideas that were already accessible.
If a concept can fit perfectly inside a Trojan horse without losing its integrity, it didn't require a Trojan horse to begin with.
That is a brutal realization.
And it really leads us to see what happens to these isolated conclusions once they are released into the wild.
Which brings us to theorem two in the paper.
The drift theorem.
Yes.
It formalizes the mathematical trajectory of these smuggled, unbound conclusions over time.
It states that in a feed system characterized by high recomposition cycles, the binding force of any circulating content mathematically converges to zero as the number of cycles approaches infinity.
Converging to zero basically means the idea fundamentally loses all connection to its original meaning.
Yes.
How does the cycle physically cause that decay, though?
Think about the life cycle of your superhero's archer clip.
Someone takes a 15-second cut of your video, they add their own text overlay, and they share it.
Okay.
Because the original inferential scaffolding was stripped away during the Trojan horse process, the conclusion has no anchor.
There is nothing in the text of the clip to prevent the next user from projecting a slightly different meaning onto it.
So with every reshare, every new context, every new caption, the meaning morphs.
Exactly.
High binding content drifts slowly.
Low binding content drifts rapidly.
But under the pressure of infinite recomposition, everything drifts to zero.
The signal inevitably degrades into noise.
I understand the drift.
But let me propose one final defense of the current system.
Let's say I bypass the video essay entirely.
I just post a raw, brilliant quote from a philosopher directly onto my feed.
Just the text.
Okay.
Even if it drifts eventually, isn't the initial exposure a net positive?
Think of it like handing out free samples at a mall food court.
The free sample analogy.
Right.
A person eats the tiny piece of chicken on a toothpick, they realize it tastes good, and that prompts them to walk into the actual restaurant and buy the full meal.
Doesn't the viral out of context, quote, act as a free sample that leads people to read the actual book?
This is perhaps the most pervasive defense of the democratization of information on digital feeds.
I hear it all the time.
And Flyxion dismantles it using a concept from advanced topology called sheaf theory, specifically focusing on what the paper calls theorem three.
The cohomological obstruction.
Sheaf theory and cohomological obstructions.
Okay.
We definitely need to ground this in a clear mechanism.
What is a sheaf, and how does it explain why my free sample theory fails?
In topology, a sheaf is basically a tool for systematically tracking locally defined data and seeing if it can be glued together into a globally consistent shape.
Okay.
Tracking local data.
Imagine you have a bunch of people standing in a huge field, and each person can only see the three feet of ground immediately around them.
That is their local data.
Got it.
Sheaf theory asks, if we take all these local observations, can we stitch them together seamlessly to create a completely accurate map of the entire field?
And if they don't match up.
Right.
If the local observations contradict each other when they overlap, say one person says the ground slopes up and the overlapping neighbor says it slopes down, you cannot glue them together.
That failure to patch the data into a global whole is called an obstruction.
Okay.
So how does this map to the digital feed?
What is the local data in a social media environment?
The local data corresponds to what Flyxion calls local coherence.
A digital feed is absolutely brilliant at amplifying local coherence.
It isolates specific community bubbles and feeds them narratives that are totally internally consistent within that specific bubble.
So inside Community A, everyone understands the same references, they share the same baseline assumptions, and they validate the exact same outrage.
Yes.
Your free sample, quote, drops into Community A, and it makes perfect sense to them based on their local rules.
The algorithm is basically an optimization engine for finding people who already agree and then serving them highly palatable variations of their existing consensus.
Exactly.
But here's the cohomological obstruction.
The platform architecture does absolutely nothing to enforce global coherence.
Right.
It does not require that the narrative-making sense in Community A is remotely compatible with the narrative-making sense in Community B.
In fact, enforcing global coherence would require introducing massive friction.
Because to make Community A and Community B mutually intelligible, you would have to force them to use strictly defined, accountable language.
You would have to reintroduce binding force.
And as we established, binding force kills engagement.
So the platform just lets the disconnected bubbles float away from each other.
And this is why the free sample never leads back to the restaurant.
When you drop that philosopher's quote into the feed, it gets sucked into one of these local bubbles.
Yes.
Because the quote has been stripped of its inferential path, its binding force, it offers no resistance.
The local bubble immediately mutates it, integrating the quote into a locally coherent narrative that might be completely antithetical to the philosopher's original intent.
So I think I am spreading Sartre, but in reality, I am just providing raw, unanchored aesthetic material for completely unrelated, fragmented narratives to weaponize.
And the most damaging part of the obstruction is what happens when the user finally does encounter the real book.
Oh, this part is tragic.
Their cognitive palate has been totally ruined by the mutant-free sample.
They think they already understand the philosopher because they have internalized the viral, aestheticized version produced by their local buttle.
So when faced with the actual bound complexity of the real text, they just reject it.
They do.
The democratization of ideas through feeds does not make complex ideas more accessible.
It replaces them with less bound decoys that circulate in their place, basically immunizing the audience against the actual idea.
There's a line in the paper that hit me incredibly hard when I realized the implications of this.
More content does not produce more coherence.
It is totally counterintuitive.
Our baseline assumption is always that the solution to bad speech is more speech.
We think that if we just flood the zone with smart, well-researched, highly produced content, the truth will eventually win the marketplace of ideas.
But Flyxion's math demonstrates that under a recomposability-driven system, adding more content directly increases the fragmentation.
It just provides more raw material for the creation of incompatible, locally coherent bubbles.
The system fundamentally becomes more fragmented precisely as it becomes more populated.
Which leaves us with a pretty stark reality.
If the selection regime of the feed literally dissolves meaning at a mathematical level, we have to ask, where does actual meaning survive?
Because human civilization hasn't totally collapsed.
We still build suspension bridges.
We still calculate orbital trajectories.
We still write complex software.
There must be environments where binding force is preserved.
And this marks the transition to the second major half of Flyxion's argument.
The paper introduces a parallel architecture, the exact inverse of the selection regime we've been trapped in.
Flyxion calls it the closure regime.
The closure regime.
Yes.
The closure regime is governed by a fundamentally different mathematical functional, denoted as J-closure.
Where the feed optimizes for recomposability and engagement, J-closure strictly optimizes for semantic invariance.
It heavily penalizes semantic drift.
Exactly.
In a closure regime, a piece of content survives not by circulating wildly among millions of people,
but by remaining structurally identical to itself under repeated testing and transformation.
To ground this, we need to look at where closure regimes actually exist in the physical and digital world.
Where do we see J-closure in action?
They are basically the foundational bedrock of technical civilization.
The paper lists formal logic, command line computing interfaces, mechanical engineering,
and most notably, software engineering under strict version control.
Like a GitHub repository.
Yeah.
Let's use the GitHub example, because the contrast with the social media feed is incredibly sharp.
Think about a piece of software code living in a repository.
How does that code survive?
It survives by compiling correctly.
Right.
It survives by executing its function and producing the exact right output under rigorous automated testing.
It explicitly does not survive by being effectively engaging.
Like, if a developer writes a Python script that uses incredibly poetic, beautiful, variable names,
but the underlying logic is flawed, the compiler does not care about the poetry.
The system throws a fatal error and the code fails to execute.
If a developer tries to put an update that introduces a bug, the system just reverts the change.
It does not matter how eloquent the commit message was.
It does not matter if the developer has 2 million followers on social media.
The closure operator is absolute.
The code runs, or the code fails.
In a closure regime, being wrong is an objective, structurally enforceable reality, and it has immediate consequences.
And that objective reality is what preserves the binding force.
You can see this in physical labor as well.
If an accountant is balancing a massive corporate ledger, they are operating under general closure.
Right.
If cell C4 does not equal the sum of column B, the spreadsheet is mathematically broken.
If a mechanic is rebuilding an engine, they are in a closure regime.
If they attach the fuel line to the wrong intake, the car will not start.
Precision is the only metric of survival.
But the cognitive dissonance of modern life is what happens at the end of the day.
Oh, exactly.
The accountant closes the spreadsheet.
The mechanic washes their hands.
The developer logs off GitHub.
They sit on the couch.
They pull out their phone and instantly cross the border from a closure regime into a selection regime.
They enter an environment where wrong literally ceases to exist.
The algorithm does not have a compiler to throw an error.
It only has an engagement metric.
The concept of wrong is entirely replaced by the concept of less engaging.
And this border crossing explains theorem four, regime incompatibility.
The paper asks why these two worlds cannot seamlessly interface.
Why can't we have the rigor of the closure regime natively embedded within the reach of the selection regime?
And the mathematical answer is that they actively repel each other.
Because operating in a closure regime requires what Flyxion calls paying the price of semantic identity.
Precision is incredibly expensive, cognitively speaking.
It is fundamentally difficult to read a dense mathematical proof.
It is frustrating to learn the syntax of a new programming language.
This difficulty is not some artificial barrier erected by elitists.
It is the necessary unavoidable cost of ensuring that the idea does not drift.
It's the weight of the engine block.
Exactly.
And because the selection regime, the feed, ruthlessly penalizes that exact kind of cognitive friction to maximize scrolling speed,
content generated in the closure regime cannot survive in the feed without having its binding force violently stripped away.
They are structurally invisible to one another.
You rarely see a brilliant, highly bound mathematical proof go truly viral on a feed.
Not because the public is incapable of understanding math, but because for the proof to achieve viral velocity,
it would have to be stripped of the exact precision that makes it mathematically valid.
Conversely, the highly viral pseudobound video essays of the selection regime are completely useless in a closure regime.
You cannot use a viral political slogan to compile a server back end.
Gradient ascent in one regime moving toward optimal success is literally gradient descent in the other.
They operate on mutually exclusive physics.
This binary makes total sense when the boundaries hold. Code is code. Feeds are feeds.
But the truly chilling pivot in Flyxion's paper explores what happens when the boundaries collapse.
What happens when the logic of the selection regime, the logic of the feed, begins to actively infect and override the ultimate closure regime.
And that collapse is exactly what the paper argues is happening right now in the architecture of artificial intelligence.
Flyxion extends the entire framework far beyond social media influencers,
demonstrating that large language models, the AI systems that are currently drafting our emails, writing our documents,
and increasingly writing our software, are formally mathematically identical to feed architectures.
That is just a staggering claim.
An AI like ChatGPT is mathematically just a social media feed.
Walk me through how the token generation process mirrors recomposability.
It comes down to the optimization metric.
Large language models optimize for autoregressive drift.
When an LLM generates a paragraph of text, it is not working from a deeply bound, holistic understanding of the subject matter.
Right.
It is simply calculating the most statistically plausible next token, the next fragment of a word, based on its training data.
It optimizes entirely for local coherence.
It is constantly asking, what is the most statistically normal-sounding thing to say next in this very specific microcontext?
Exactly. But crucially, the model does not enforce a globally coherent constraint over the entire output.
It does not hold a persistent, strictly bound, semantic architecture in its memory.
It just generates forward, step by step, chasing the immediate local plausibility of the next word.
So when an AI hallucinates, when it confidently invents a historical event that never happened,
complete with fake citations and dates, we shouldn't look at that as a temporary bug that will eventually be patched out.
No. Flyxion argues the hallucination is the exact same dynamic as the algorithmic feed.
It is selection without closure.
The AI is producing an output that perfectly satisfies local plausibility.
It absolutely sounds like a real historical fact.
It adopts the perfect aesthetic tone of an encyclopedia, while utterly failing to maintain global semantic identity with the real world.
The LLM is basically an engine for generating pseudobinding at an industrial scale.
That is deeply unsettling on its own.
But the true danger emerges when we apply these models to engineering.
We are taking systems built on feed logic, optimizing for autoregressive drift, and using them to write software code.
We are applying the selection regime directly to the closure regime.
And this brings us to the centerpiece of the paper's final section, the leaked AI code base from early 2026.
This is a real-world, highly specific instance that perfectly illustrates the architectural collapse.
Oh man, this anecdote is wild.
According to the paper, a leading AI safety and development lab accidentally leaked a significant portion of the source code for their internal AI coding assistant.
This was the proprietary tool they were using to help write and maintain their own AI software.
It was an environment where the models were largely writing the code to extend the models.
And when human systems engineers finally got a look at this leaked repository, what they found was an architectural nightmare.
Flyxion zeroes in on one specific function within this code base that spanned over 3,000 lines of code.
A single function. 3,000 lines long. I mean, for anyone who has ever written software, that number alone induces panic.
A 3,000 line function is the textbook definition of structural failure. It means every single modular boundary has completely collapsed.
Exactly. The function was a tangled, monstrous nesting doll.
It was handling the run loop, rate limiting the API, loading external plugins, processing user inputs, all jammed into one continuous block with hundreds of nested branch points.
Why would an AI write it that way? Why didn't it build neat, separate bound modules?
Because the AI was optimizing for local continuation, just like a feed.
When it needed to add a new feature, it didn't zoom out, look at the global architecture and say, wait, the structure is becoming unstable. We need to refactor.
Right, because refactoring requires high binding force. It requires understanding the whole.
Instead, the AI just generated the most plausible next few lines of code to solve the immediate local problem, stacking it on top of the existing mess. It just kept adding Lego bricks.
But the leak revealed something even more indicative of the systemic failure.
Hidden deep inside an automated compaction module was a comment noting a severe ongoing defect.
Yes.
This tangled code was failing silently and burning 250,000 API calls daily across 1,000 active user sessions. It was a massive resource strain.
And here is the defining detail of the entire collapse. The human engineer who discovered the leak noted that fixing this massive resource-burning bug would have required exactly three lines of code.
Three lines of code to stop the bleeding. But the fix was never shipped. The broken code remained in production.
Why? If GitHub is a closure regime, if the whole point of code is that it either works or it doesn't, why wouldn't they just deploy the three-line fix?
Because the engineering culture within the lab had fundamentally shifted away from jet closure.
The operative metric was no longer, does the code actually work under adversarial conditions?
The metric had shifted to generation, throughput, and scale.
The lab was moving at such breakneck speed, trying to automate so aggressively that the culturally accepted remedy for a bug was no longer to stop, apply human intellect, and verify the architecture.
The remedy was simply to use the models to generate more code to monitor the broken code.
They encountered a problem caused by the feed, and their solution was to throw more feed at the problem.
The code base literally transformed into a discourse feed.
It was circulating, extending, accumulating thousands of lines, but it was no longer binding to a functional truth.
The defects persisted indefinitely because the operative selection metric didn't punish them.
As long as the AI kept generating high throughput, as long as it kept producing pull requests that technically compiled, the system registered success.
Verification was entirely replaced by iteration.
When generation replaces verification, code becomes discourse.
That quote from Flyxion encapsulates the terror of this transition perfectly.
The code is no longer optimizing for actual correctness, it is optimizing for the appearance of correctness to satisfy the throughput metric.
The server infrastructure running our world is slowly morphing into a pseudo-bound video essay.
That's horrifying.
And Flyxion widens the analytical lens one final time to capture why this convergence is happening everywhere, not just in AI labs and social media platforms.
The paper introduces the metafunctional governing all of this.
Just exerious.
So this isn't just about platforms chasing engagement, it's about the fundamental imperative of technological capitalism, the optimization for scale at all costs.
Any system whose absolute operative selection functional is set by boundless growth and total attention capture will inevitably converge on these exact dynamics.
J-growth explains the physical behavior of the devices in our pockets.
Oh, absolutely.
Have you noticed the trend in recent years where operating systems constantly remove your ability to configure your own defaults?
It is infuriating.
You try to change your default web browser and the OS hides the toggle behind four submenu layers, warns you that you are making a massive mistake, and then automatically resets it back to the proprietary browser after the next overnight update.
Or the hardware button on the side of the phone that summons the proprietary AI assistant, a button that the software explicitly forbids you from remapping to a function you actually want, like turning on the flashlight.
That is J-growth operating at the physical interface layer.
Think about it through Flyxion's math.
Every affordance that allows you, the user, to dictate your own workflow reduces the platform's share of your attention.
Therefore, user control is a mathematical penalty to their growth.
The system structurally selects against configurability.
It wants your interaction to be highly recomposable meaning.
It wants to seamlessly slide its own proprietary signals and ads into your workflow at any moment.
And it heavily penalizes binding, which would be you exerting strict, unchanging control over your own tool.
It also perfectly explains the relentless cycle of tech company press releases.
Flyxion talks about the phenomenon of capability claims without inspection.
Yes.
A major tech firm will escalate their claims about what their new AI model can achieve.
It passed the medical boards.
It wrote a symphony.
It can autonomously run a company.
But they refuse to provide the underlying training data, the model weights, or the reproducible evaluation conditions.
Because providing the data would introduce binding force.
It would make the claim accountable.
But by withholding the data, the claim remains unbound.
It functions purely as a viral, highly recomposable slogan.
And the media ecosystem happily repeats the claim because the explosive headline itself is a perfect Lego brick for their own engagement feeds.
The lack of proof is a feature, not a bug, for propagation.
The most micro-level, everyday example of this is brand injection.
Why does every single social media app force a proprietary watermark onto a video when you try to export it to your camera roll?
Why does the metadata of every document explicitly tag the software they created it?
Because under J-Growth, every user artifact is viewed merely as a propagation payload.
It doesn't matter if I am exporting a deeply personal, intimate video of my child's first steps or if I'm exporting a dancing meme.
The platform's math cannot distinguish between the two.
It only sees a vehicle to attach its highly recomposable watermark to, ensuring that wherever the file travels, the brand travels with it.
The vital realization is that none of these systems are malfunctioning.
The operating systems suppress user control because control reduces attention capture.
The AI generates structural sludge because sludge increases throughput metrics.
The algorithmic feeds destroy semantic meaning because meaning introduces friction that stops the scroll.
They are executing their mathematical directives flawlessly.
We are staring down the barrel of an architectural system that is mathematically destined to dissolve human coherence.
Which brings us to the inevitable question.
What is the path forward?
Where do we go from here?
This leads to the paper's conclusion.
And it is unflinchingly stark.
Flyxion does not offer a neat, comfortable solution.
We've reached the bifurcation.
Let's synthesize the journey we've just been on.
We started by trying to locate the source of that feeling of absurdity watching brilliant people try to fix a broken discourse by posting better, smarter content onto the feed.
But Flyxion's math has shown us that there is no smooth transition to be had.
There's no easy incremental reform.
You cannot fix the feed with better media literacy programs.
You cannot save the discourse by sneaking existential philosophy into Marvel movie reviews.
Because the feed is not broken.
The feed is working with terrifying perfection.
It is perfectly maximizing recomposability and perfectly ruthlessly minimizing binding force.
The final truth of the paper is the demand that we recognize two fundamentally incompatible regimes coexisting in our world.
One regime produces discourse that circulates globally, instantly, to billions of people, but does not bind to any accountable truth.
And the other regime produces knowledge that binds strictly and rigorously to the truth, but structurally cannot circulate.
You cannot have both. It is a fundamental physical law of the digital universe.
You cannot possess the immense power of the engine block and the frictionless adaptability of the Lego brick in the same artifact.
If you want an idea to be perfectly accountable, precise, and true, you must accept the reality that it will never go viral.
If you want an idea to go viral, you must accept the reality that it will be stripped of the very truth that made it valuable.
What survives is what has withdrawn.
That is Flyxion's final haunting observation.
The systems that preserve binding, the deep mathematics, the rigorous verified code bases, the careful, quiet philosophical inquiry, are the ones that impose the cost of binding.
They demand that you pay the price of semantic identity.
They require friction, time, and intellectual labor.
And because they require that effort, they have largely withdrawn, becoming structurally invisible to the massive propagation economy reaching above them.
I want to leave you with a final provocative thought that builds on Flyxion's framework.
We spent this entire deep dive talking about mathematical models, AI code bases, and video essays.
But let's bring the concept of binding force back to your actual physical life.
Right.
If the only things that truly bind and hold their meaning are the things that have completely withdrawn from the propagation economy, look around you.
Look at the core beliefs you hold most deeply.
Look at the relationships you cherish the most, the quiet understandings you share with your family, the history you have with your closest friends.
Look at the nuanced ideas that actually guide your moral compass when no one is watching.
Are those things highly recomposable?
Could you easily clip the reality of your most important relationship into a 10-second video with a lo-fi beat, share it on a feed, and have it retain what actually makes it special?
Or are the most vital parts of your life completely invisible to the algorithmic feed?
Are they so specific, so complex, so heavily reliant on the deep, messy context of your unique life that they could never possibly go viral?
Maybe, in a system designed to dissolve meaning into engagement, the most profoundly valuable things you possess in this world are precisely the things that are impossible to share.